so this is from the anutra nikaya from
the book of the
F the discourse with the Camas of
kuta so have I heard at one time the
Buddha was wandering in the land of the
calans together with a large sa of
buikus when he arrived at the town of
the kalas named
kuta the kalas of kuta heard it seems
the atic Goa the sakan gone forth from a
sakang family has arrived at quesam muta
he has this good reputation that blessed
one is in arat fully awakened Buddha and
so on and then they come to the
conclusion it is good to see such
Arad then the Camas went up to the
Buddha before sitting down to one side
some bowed some exchanged pleasantries
some h held up their joint Palms towards
the Buddha some announced their name and
Clan while some kept
silent SE to One S the Kal said to the
Buddha bante there are some athetics and
brahans who come to quesam muta they
explain and promote only their own
Doctrine while they attack divide
disparage and smear the doctrines of
others then some other Aesthetics and
brahans come to kuta they too explain
and promote only their own Doctrine
while they attack divite disparates and
smear the doctrines of others so Vante
where doubting and
uncertain I wonder who of these
respected Aesthetics and brahmins speak
the truth and who speaks
falsehood then the Buddha replies it is
appropriate kalas for you to be doubting
and uncertain doubt has come up in you
about an uncertain
matter kalas don't go by Oral
transmission by lineage by hearsay by
canonical Authority by Logic by
inference by analysis of properties by
the acceptance of riew after
consideration by the appearance of
competence or by the thought the
aesthetic is our respected teacher when
you know for yourselves these things are
detrimental blameworthy criticized by
sensible people and when undertaken they
lead to harm and suffering then you
should give them
up what do you think Camas when greed
arises in a person does it do so for
their welfare or harm and then the kalas
reply harm bante a greedy individual
overcome by greed kills living creatures
steals commits adultery lies and
encourages others to do the same is that
for their lasting harm and suffering yes
Vante what do you think Camas when a
version arises in a person and then
repeats and then it also talks about
when um delusion arises in a
person um that's all detrimental and
blame worthy then the Buddha says so Camas
worthy then the Buddha says so Camas
when I said don't go by old transmission
by lineage by hearsay by canonical
Authority by Logic inference by analysis
of properties by the acceptance of
review after consideration by the
appearance of competence or by the
thought the aesthetic is our respected
teacher then when you know for yourselves these
then when you know for yourselves these
things are detrimental blameworthy
criticized by sensible people and when
undertaken they lead to harm and
suffering then you should give them up
that is what I said and that is why I
said it and then um it continues for in
the opposite way so when you know non-
greet arises in a person non aversion
arises in a person and um non delusion
or middle minded arises in the person
then uh you should know for yourself
that that's beneficial and uh not
blameworthy uh then the Su continues and
says then that Noble disciple is rid of
longing rid of ill will un muddled aware
and recollected he abides having
pervaded with a mind of friendliness the
first Direction likewise second third
and fourth in the same way the Brahma
huh yes the Brahma these are the Brahma
viharas yes in the same way above below
across everywhere he abides having
pervaded the whole world with a mind of
friendliness abundant expansive
immeasurable free of enmity and ill will
and so it goes on for the other three
Brahma viharas um so this is one of the more
viharas um so this is one of the more
well-known um discourses the discourses
to the calamas and there's quite a few
things to unpack here so perhaps you can
start um with with the very first thing
that the Buddha says like call by
tradition right oral transmission
transmission logical inference or uh you
know accepting a view after pondering it
and so on if you don't do any of
that then what do you do and then how do
you know that you're practicing rightly
what do people here say
my first thought is that he's not
necessarily dismissing these things as
tools um in the sense like he's not
saying oh you know don't go by Logic a
false conclusion to draw from that would
be like okay then that means the dhama
doesn't have to be
logical um or like things don't have to
make sense um but what I what I get from
that is more don't fall into a
complacency of like okay just because
you've made this logical analysis of
you've you've put every suta into a box
you can draw all the parallels it all
makes perfect sense no
contradictions um not to like if that's
kind of your your
Baseline then you're you're going to be
missing the Mark still and and and why
what is what is it that all those things
have in common but that still makes it
not dhama it's not
dhama it's not
personal let's
say it's not personal but some people
can be very personal about accepting a
teacher for example
right or after having spent like 20 30
years pondering a VI coming to the
conclusion this must be right and that
bu comes along is as well the fact that
you've pondered it for a long time
doesn't necessarily mean correct
mhm so so can there be a is is there a
more accurate
Factor I'm trying to think of something
to say that's not just kind of what he
followed up with but since you
like is it on that personal level
where even if that
uh the teacher dies the beloved teacher
um and you forget everything they ever
said can you
still are you still free well like like
like the Buddha says do you still know
right from wrong do you still know
Liberation the thing there is
um the funny thing the is that the
second part is usually left out it's
usually just like okay don't go by
tradition don't go by hearsay don't go
by Logic and people quote that as a kind
of um a testament to how Buddhism is
different from other religions where
it's like your
own uh experience is is the measure or
something and then the thing is that
Carri is the implication that it's
almost like like make your own truth or
something like that like there's some
individual truth and you're supposed to
pick where resonates with you and remove
the rest or something but uh it actually
says there what is it that you it's
implied though but it says what is it
that you're supposed to use as a
standard and it says when greed aversion
and delusion
arises so
um what you said just now of keeping it
personal the thing is like that that's
exactly what it is but you don't do it
just by
uh because you can be personal
but objective and that's the problem the
problem is like all these uh
permutations of of attitudes the issue
with them is you think that something
objective something external something
that's public is what determines right
and wrong yeah that's what all those
things to a degree have in common yeah
yeah so even if it's as it says your own
logic and reasoning it's something
objective that means like okay every
every day I do this it's right because
logically I have made all the the right
connections like it makes sense
logically but if you do something with a
mind of
greed even if it makes sense even if
it's what the teacher said even if it's
what the Traditions said it's wrong
because it's done with the mind of greed
in in other words the the uh what is
rooted in greed aversion and
delusion that is the truth and that's
not um the so presence of greed aversion
and delusion and absence of greed
aversion and delusion that's the truth
that's the criteria yeah yeah that's
that's like
uh that's not debatable in in the sense
that you're either acting with those
things or not MH and that's that's the
um it what I'm saying is it's not it's
not saying that there are different
truths or something like that that that
that you need to find your own it's
saying um that's the only def defining
criteria for so that is universal but
not objective yeah exactly so it's
because not just objective in the terms
of individual people but in terms of
yourself as well like one morning you
can be
having um you can be doing something
that's seemingly good like helping
someone let's say and in the morning
it's rooted in a in a mind of non-greed
non aversion you out of a genuine
intention you were just helping this
person but in the evening you're doing
it again and now it's rooted in just a
desire for company and distu
M so it's it's like
ual desire or whatever M so if you think
that okay the Buddha said that helping
people is good the Buddha said that you
know it makes sense that it's that it's
wholesome and whatever and you think of
it about it in that objective sense you
would Overlook that actually was
defining the action is what state of
mind you have right now yes and um so
it's and the the actions that it says
there um while the precepts in
themselves they're like if it were possible to kill
they're like if it were possible to kill
without a mind of aversion to steal
without a mind of aversion to lie
without a mind of aversion to or or
mindal greet or delusion for that matter
yeah yeah yeah or any kind of un hosome
mental state and these things wouldn't
be wrong MH it doesn't matter what the
tradition says what matters is these
things are wrong because they always
carry those mental days yeah um
so from that point if if somebody's
following the
precepts just because the tradition says
that you need to follow the precepts and
because that's that's what Buddhists do
uh that means that they haven't
understood the principle and they're not
trying to understand the principle of
what makes those things wholesome and
what makes the what what makes the
abstinence from those things wholesome
MH U so and it's the fact that
yeah to to that extent you you'd have a
mindset of less greed less aversion and
less delusion and you take that as your
standard and then you take that
principle further but if you just stay
on that um that happens often like
people uh with meditation and stuff
especially like you you there's this
tendency to assume that okay if I just
do this if I just go through these
motions every day every time I do it
it's going to be
wholesome that means you're because
somebody told you really it's like
somebody told you that if you repeat
these things eventually you will get to
Enlightenment and that's again depending
on depending fully on um tradition or
hearsay and and you're not seeing what
is the mental state that I have
presently yeah is it a mindset of
creativ verion or delusion so that I can
if I know that I can directly cultivate
Liberation I don't need to wait for yes
some miracle to happen after I do this
practice for 10 years so this is with
the [Music]
[Music]
external component there Conformity is
often involved finding safety in just in
even if it's self-imposed I'm going to
do this every time in the morning and in
the evening which then allows you to
completely Overlook right sign of the
mind and where intentions actually are
which is the factor there and this
almost seems to me like a sort of
further elaboration of what would be
involved in that factor ofas which which
prevents one it's one of the first three
factors that prevent one from becoming a
noble disciple and interestingly enough
that Su continues after the Buddha has
listed that and he says then this Noble
disciple knows that his mind is right so
and then it's kind like well hang on
hang on a minute how did it suddenly go
from kalas confused and then the Buddha
suddenly in introducing noyle well
actually all of that's implied yeah yeah
because if you understand if you fully
actually the the majima 9 it defines
what is a noble disciple the very first
thing it says it's somebody who
understands wholesome and un wholesome
and understands the root of the
wholesome and the root of the UN
wholesome and what is that root great
aversion and delusion non great non
aversion of delusion so if you take that
principle to the full extent and as you
see it starts with the precepts that's
why that's like the level where everyone
will be able to see this like if they're
have a basic of self honesty they will
see that doing those things carries more
great diversion delusion than not non
not doing those things and with that as
a basis they can start then refining it
further to the point where okay verbal
actions and then finally mental actions
which is how you would cultivate some in
the end yeah so um yeah so maybe we can
also clear up like I mean in the
beginning there will be greet a version
and illusion that's the starting point
so it's not black and white like there's
either full-blown GRE and illusion or
there's nothing but it will sort of
right so you can compare your own
experience to a degree and you can see
this is this is less greedy m
this is lesser version so you can still
it's not completely absent but within
that you can still see this is moving in
the right direction this is certainly
moving away from it and that is the
refining of the principle yeah like I
said it's it's from this starting point
that you are what mind do I have what
like you would see for yourself if I if
I just somebody who's not keeping the
five precepts let say they would see
clearly that if they abstain from those
things it will be moving in the opposite
direction of greed diversion and
delusion um so but if if then you just
take it as um that's actually why you
would be able to skip the development of
virtue many times wrongly of course
because um you haven't actually
understood like why those precepts are
are wholesome you just take them
conditionally because you think well it
it comes bundled with the whole other
aspects of the practice and then and you
never actually understood why that
Foundation was was important so then it
feels like you're progressing but really
like the progress was elsewhere the
progress was in understanding why these
things were wholesome it it was not in
all the other stuff that came afterward
when you were doing your meditation
that's in a sense secondary yeah yeah so
so because the Buddha doesn't talk about
getting special experiences the Buddha
talks about understanding what mental
states are there when you have
experiences mhm so then if you assume
that just having experiences is is
what's what what's wholesome you would
Overlook that there can be mental states
of longing greed and all these sorts of
things yeah you're talking about people
trying to get special experiences based
on some meditation practice for example
and and actually it's it's there when it
talks about the Brahma viharas after the
noble disciple has understood the
freedom from longing aversion and all
these things because if you haven't
understood those mental States and you
try to cultivate any type of meditation
you will be doing it out of what you
heard just following a set of external
instructions even if it's correct even
if it's the Buddha himself who gave you
those instructions fundamentally it
won't be wholesome because you're not
seeing it as you don't see why it's
beneficial and and as budha said the
destruction of defilements can only
happen for one who understands it cannot
happen like like fortuitously just I
just did this because he told me to do
it and then I I got the result if you
don't if you don't see where you're
going even before you start walking you
you cannot get there
mhm yeah so presence of GRE hated and
illusion or absence that is actually
what is directly visible dhama exactly
here now whereas a tradition or
pondering a view all all of that is
either not directly visible
or it it is not as
immediate um as seeing whether right now
that that mind state is affected by
greed hatred and and delusion and and
and that understanding cannot be taken
away and it would actually distract you
putting emphasis on those things would
actually distract you because you know
there's for with the precepts as well
for example um you know you often have
uh the the sort of tcid implication in
like spiritual communities and stuff
that if we just adhere to to this same
behavior we are
automatically just you take it on you're
supposed to take it on faith that we're
automatically going the right direction
if you just adhere to this no questions
asked and um that inherently is is
actually distracting you from um from
figuring out what is if even if it's
wholesome like even if it's something
that the suas talk about yeah party
training for mon for example but if you
take it as like no no I just do this and
that's good you're actually obstructing
your own your own progress cuz you're
not you you you uh left
the the work undone of of discerning
those in those background intentions so
um and then and another thing is uh is
you said directly visible dma that's
exactly what another thing it's
overlooked like as Buddha said the dhama
is supposed to to be directly visible so
if the dhama depends on some experience
you're supposed to have the come later
mhm then is not directly visible yeah
and precisely if you into when there is
that time interval I'm doing this and
I'm waiting for result it's that's great
yeah but that's also
doubt right be because you're doing
something now and as long as you don't
have a confirmation that you're doing it
right you don't know whether you're
doing it right because it's not
immediately directly visible
and were you all people do this do that
so that so so that doubt has to be
squeezed out by seeing that right now
you can check for yourself individually
whether there greed hatred and illusion
or not the the moment it becomes uh time
bound which is how most people
unfortunately approach their meditation
practice you will never be able to
transend outs and and and even if you
get some special experience then you
would still need to infer afterwards oh
it must be because of done this and that
but even then you don't quite know
actually that's a good one like you know
you you have the experience but then you
need to go to the teacher to confirm
like oh was it was this the right one
yeah and and then he then he looks it up
in the books and the canonical Authority
and it says oh yeah on page 227 it's
confirmed here so it must be right yeah
but this is or you get a certificate
confirming that yes you did get the Tre
entry or something like uh um
and and as as it was saying the the
these different people they have
different um listen to different
teachers and you see all of those
teachers if they wanted to they could
prescribe this path of training that if
you get to you follow through it you
will get to this magical Revelation and
they can all say that you know that
Revelation is nibana and the columnist
would be totally unable to decide which
one is the right one uh but you would
only be be able to know so which of
those paths would actually be more in
line with a mind of non- greed non
aversion and non delusion that would be
the final criteria and um that's the
that's like
the for for anything for the for the
athetics and brahans back in the
Buddhist time that we not practicing as
wrongly it's not because they would they
were adhering
to uh you know external guidelines and
and traditional aspects that that were
in line with Buddhism it's simply
because they did actually to some extent
understand the principle of abandoning G
diversion and delusion it's not because
they were doing the right J technique or
something that that's again dependent on
canonical Authority or whatever they
might have completely different ideas
about everything but the point is
internally they have to some extent gone
in that direction of taming these UNH
wholesome states in the mind not out of
just just um uh doing what what a
teacher says
mhm I do think it might be worth just
kind of talking a little bit more even
about the whole view
of kind of the view of morality being an
external I think you were saying you
were saying earlier something can be
personal but
objective that is a
extremely like in ingrained view in the
west especially these days just the like
it's all about kind of consequences of
your actions whether you intend that or
not um is sort of just today's social
standard like that's that's how you
judge some if I do something
unintentionally but it results in a bad
consequence then it's immoral right yeah
that's the yeah that's that's the way of
viewing things these days and it it
totally ignores that
internal criteria which is what like you actually
criteria which is what like you actually
have to work with yeah as opposed to
just like mathematically calculating if
I do this I should account for a
butterfly flapping its wings 200 years
ago my like
yeah yeah it's it's uh you need to use
then the the standard of the internal state
the the standard of the internal state
of mind because I mean the Buddha
himself when he for
example prescrib theba meditation and
these I don't know how many monks ended
up committing
suicide um there was no certainly no
internal desire in him for that to
happen and yet it was not un wholesome
because his mind at that point it wasn't
it didn't have great verion delusion so
then if you think like
um killing stealing all the things that
that the precepts uh prohibit they're
bad because of what they do to other
people uh then you would actually you
might even justify breaking precepts
with that logic because you could say
well certain things abstain standing
from certain things actually makes other
people feel b or makes their life more
difficult or whatever so then you would
think Al I should actually break these
things but no it's that internal
criteria um means that well the
the the benefit that comes to you and
the benefit that comes to others will
usually not be in the dimension of
benefit that you conceive to be which is
like just pleasure it's in the diens of
uh not further cultivating these states
not only in yourself but in
others so like sexual intercourse for
example you could think oh by not doing
this I am actually maybe making another
person unhappy but that's not the
criteria for what's beneficial it's like
um actually as a Buddha said in that
other Su where it says that
um there are people who can happily
engage in killing stealing lying and all
the UNH wholesome States and then there
are people who uh sadly like with with
pain and suffering engage in these
things so that's not what makes it right
or wrong like how they
feel um
so it's all just that internal Dimension
that again it's not like even Up For
Debate once you start seeing it uh you
one day your mind is with a greedy has
it has a greedy inclination even if the
whole world says no you should be able
to do this from the point of view of
dhama you don't you don't do
it that's actually why the S say that
sat becomes independent of the uh of
anyone anybody else's instruction yeah
cuz not because they just acquired this
logical standard because it says that's
not what matters they acquired some
perfect system of of thought about
around how to practice it's because at
any time they see their mental state so
even if well actually even in in a
future life because as s to say you know
s could be reborn up to seven times and
whatnot they would no longer have the
information of the the Buddhist teaching
that they acquired in the previous site
but what they would have is they still
see their own mind mhm so that's that's
the the standard of what's wholesome and
un wholesome the actual standard would
remain um
so that's another thing like any of
these uh relying on any of these things
means that well all you have to do
really to not be able to practice
anymore is get Alzheimer's or dementia
and or you already lost the basis of
your practice but yeah so even all the
information that you have accumulated
even if it is the right information
right when that's a good contemplation
when when all that goes right when all
the books are burned all the teachers
all the YouTube talks all all all the
rest of it finished you are on your own
and you don't know any of those
instructions anymore right ex uh
instructions in the sense of external in
information then are you sufficiently
independent to carry on with your
practice towards final goal
right but even without those like
because uh the even if the intellectual
Clarity Fades the the system of dumo or
whatever goes away do you still see mind
of greed is mind of greed mind of
aversion is mind of aversion with any
without any need for other sort of um
intermediary ways of of defining that
you just see it directly this is a mind
of greed this is a mind of aversion and
I don't te out of this that's the that's
the problem usually
that uh most practitioners don't see a
problem with the fact that they need to
use these
intermediary sort of tools M to
determine what is good or bad in terms
of in terms of the practice yeah so
that's not enough directly visible
there's a buffer in between there that
that needs to come up for interrogation
at some point yeah which is like
sometimes it might even just be how
something makes you feel you assume that
as a criteria for what the the meaning
that that's beneficial and people would
say that like if or this practice makes
me feel better than this other one that
means that this one is yeah therefore
I'm suffering L where actually because
as I said that the Buddha said you can
be doing UNH wholesome things with
perfect joy and happiness yeah so um
it's it's a it's not enough to to think
in those
terms and
um
the a further thing to note is that the
development of of all of the things s to
talk about as as we mentioned before
it's um the practices have to be
informed by your discernment of what
greed of verion and delusion is whereas
usually we take it the other way around
it's like these practices will lead me
to see what greed div verion and
delusion is but no seeing what greed
diversion and delusion is is is what
makes these practi is Right MH that's
why the whole path starts with the Right
View mhm um so it's not that you just
like the dangas is is a good example
like you assume okay I just stick to
these determinations I will not lie down
I will not uh you know uh eat from from
as a monk like I will not eat from I
will only eat a food for arms around out
of one bow one session I will sleep in
the forest I won't do this I won't do
that and then you just assume okay this
sticking to this will lead me to mhm the
understanding whereas no it's it's like
having the understanding would allow you
to contextualize those practices yeah
because somebody could be doing that out
of aversion for example yeah yeah or
conceit or or all sorts of expectations
that they're not aware of because they
don't see that as important they're
fully focused on some
objective um basis of like what somebody
else told them and what they expect to
come from it yeah and so when somebody
gets this main principle that it is the
greed hatred and delusion that is The
Guiding Factor there not all the other
practices that that are coming now then
there can still be doubt as to what is
the extent of the greed what is the
extent of the aversion what is the
extent of the of the delusion when
somebody finds themsel still in that
intermediate space so to speak um then
what would be good advice for them to
carry on well that's why the Buddha
formulated the gradual training so
actually we already did a talk on that
it's it's the you cannot understand even
if you want to like the extent of greed
that's involved in the five hindrances
for example if you haven't uh developed
your mind to transcend the the GRE div
version delusion of bodly in verbal
actions yes so that's why you you start
with that and and it says when the monk
is accomplished in virtue then I tell
him to be sensor strange when the Monk
Is accomplishing sensor strange then I
tell him to be uh moderate and eing and
so on because these are just layers of
cre diversion and delusion that you're
progressively working with um but the
even just with the basic precepts if you
keep them out of that sense of
complacency because um again because that's what the
because um again because that's what the
other monks are doing or something or
out of Duty yeah sense of Duty sense of
or the conditional sense of of like okay
if I just do this it will help the other
stuff that I actually regard as
important then you never actually even
took up the first thread of
understanding greed of verion of
the and you can review your mental
States like that's that's the practice
like uh when you're restrained but then when
uh when you're restrained but then when
the desire arises to do these things
that you made a determination to give up
is that Pleasant or unpleasant like is
that suffering or is it is it is it cuz
see you might
Overlook the the fact that as it says
greed brings harm and suffering because
you usually are able to get what you
want quickly enough but what happens
when you just have the greed but you
don't do anything is that Pleasant or
unpleasant and you will see that it's
it's quite quite um it is what suffering
is basically so from that point of view
you get to see like oh all this like the
the in the in the past when I was
regarding these actions as pleasant it's
just because like the pleasure of the
things I was getting was distracting me
from the pain of the mental state that
was actually driving me to do those
things yeah but then also sometimes
people who say no no just the desire
itself is already Pleasant is is is is
usually more pleasant because when you
then actually get what you desire it's
always a disappointment right so they
then widely see that even if they get
what they want it's initially pleasant
but afterwards it becomes a
disappointment then they say therefore I
just stick on the level of the actual
desire so as to avoid the disappointment
of actually getting it failing to see
that even the desire is more unpleasant
still but why because it doesn't leave
you alone it it's basically pushing you
to act out yeah and and it's the same
with the ill will and the aversion it is
not just optional like oh you could do
this no no it is it is very much pushing
you in that
which at the same time you know is not
wholesome and so when the mind is
overcome by these unome states that
cannot be peace because it's forcing you
to act yeah right and if you think it's
not forcing me well are you sure that
you are fully withdrawn from all the
forms of GRE diversion that's then it so
when there's doubt well I don't feel
pressed by my mind well then people can
either refine their precepts or
introduce these further steps of the
Casual training such as sens restraints
motivation in eating don't need to be a
monk for that many people nowadays will
have plenty of opportunity to experiment
with these things and then see if your
mind remains as calm and composed as you
think it now is and then you will get to
see refine that principle okay that now
there's cre diversion delusion and you
will get to see that on on a on a more
subtle level if you act out of it it's
going to be for your harm and then you
have a direct criteria to see that that
is UN wholesome yeah and then you also
see that the Buddha said that that
that's the case but now you have some
amount of direct confirmation yes that
is not just uh and that is how the doubt
goes right yeah and also um it's even
for people who are practicing as it as
it says there uh there's the acquisition
of a view after after consideration or
the it's uh it's easy to then um when
you get to a certain point in the
practice this start confusing that um
the fact that things make sense with
understanding uhhuh and um because again
it's it becomes sort of that objective
Direction even if it's correct even if
if you read the suas and you factually
understood and then like you know it
agrees that's already quite a quite a
lofty goal by the way that's very rare
but even if you get to that point but
you still don't um see it on that
internal level then that's that's
literally not the D yeah that's even if
the the information is the same yeah CU
it says like the dhama can only be known
for themselves by the wise yeah this is
why it seems to me that the dhama cannot
be a system because a system even if it
is fully internally coherent is always
something separate from from you so most
people they will be doing things that
are also contradictory but even if those
contradictions are resolved and you say
that's a system OB Ive independently
then no it it has to be you need to
become involved and and and the moment
you become involved in the system you
can never see the totality of it because
now in a sense you are in it so you have
to discern from within that mind state
so it cannot be objective system yeah
yeah it's uh the dma always applies to
you it's not it's never an
external um collection of information it's always
um collection of information it's always
the Dum is about
it's like a mirror yeah however coherent
or logical it might be which is better
than being incoherent and in logical but
but that is not the final criteria it's
like a like a mirror that you you're
sort of like examining its properties
mhm whereas the actual purpose of the
mirror is supposed to to show you like
yourself exactly but you're here
occupied with like yeah it's 3 cm thick
and it's that's basically when you're
when you're
um relating to the D that level of
information
yeah yeah I wanted to ask as well like
um like in the part of the of the suta
the Buddha says like so ating with um
acting with a mind of like gried
aversion or delusion is something un
awesome and then it goes like after the
the part after he say like acting with a
GD of non GD non diversion non delusion
is wholesome it doesn't say like um like
acting with a mind of Love acting with a
mind of like whatever peace or Joy or
whatever and I wanted to ask like why is
that so and how is why is that important
for someone
to understand that because if you don't
like he cannot bring himself to to that
you still see that as something external
to himself yeah yeah well the the thing
is um
whenever you approach it through that
angle of cultivating positive qualities
without having abandoned the negative
qualities first it always becomes like a
cover up it always becomes something
that um that's actually like you don't
want to acknowledge the fact that there
would be greed if you don't uh actively
fabricate uh non- greed or or um
renunciation let's say you don't want to
acknowledge the fact that there would be
aversion if you don't actively fabricate
love so the like for as long as the
person thinks that they need to approach
these things as as activities as things
that they do they don't see that
actually those things would arise by
themselves if they abandon the greed of
version delusion they they don't see as
that s says like that the defilements
are not inherent to the mind it's like
they they
come sort of U
gratuitously so if you remove those
defilements like if you you kind of a
you have a light bulb you don't need to
like make it
shine if it's like if it's not shining
because it's covered by something you
don't fix it by making it Shine more you
fix it by actually removing what's
abstracting it and then the light bulb
is just how it's supposed to be so
that's why the Buddha said if you don't
don't understand that principle he said
there is no development of the mind it's
just they're just covering up of one
thing with another and yeah the the the
uh development of whatever uh active
qualities like
renunciation love and uh wisdom if you
think it's that's what it's saying where
in reality it's saying non- greed non
inversion non
delusion uh that would always be
dependent on as as we said these
external sort of uh Dimensions like
somebody told you how to
cultivate um pronunciation love or whatever you
um pronunciation love or whatever you
didn't see it for
yourself that's when it would be yeah
and also there would be actually
logically a contradiction in that like
how can you gradually build up love if
if if a verion hasn't been abandoned
that's a contradiction you cannot have
aversion and at the same time start
start building up love or or or
friendliness so the so right so so the
friendliness begins with the complete
absence of the aversion so so the whole
thing is an uncovering or an undoing and
this is also why this famous oada patim
Moka right which is sometimes quoted as
like a summary of what the Buddha
teaches the first line is that he
refrains from doing something un
wholesome and then he develops what is
wholesome it it doesn't start by saying
you develop what is wholesome and then
afterwards you could consider whether
you also undo what is UN wholesome it
doesn't say that yeah yeah actually
that's the order of the for right
drivings yes it's always abandoning uh
preventing the restraining uh unisen and
wholesome States from arising abandoning
Arisen un wholesome States then you're
in the position to cultivate unisen un
wholesome States and finally you have to
protect the Arisen wholesome States
that's right so uh that's the that's the
main issue with that it's as well is is
the the aspect of timelessness that we
mentioned it's not a the DH is supposed
to be directly visible yeah so what
happens if somebody can't get themselves
to to to feel love mhm then like the the
benefit of the dma wouldn't be directly
visible because it takes time to change
your mind to force it to have these
states but if it's about non- greed well
that's always presently possible it's
about not making a choice of greed not
making a choice of a verion m that's
always directly available yeah and even
when the mind is affected by greed to
not act out by Body speech or as we
discussed earlier on the mental level
right that is already how there is that
Purity so so then the mind can still be
affected by let's say sensuality but
there would be Purity as long as there's
no acting out by Body speech and mind
yeah and that doesn't depend on time and
and it doesn't depend on you on somebody
else telling you like if you do this you
end up with loved later on that's right
non acting out doesn't depend on time
yeah yeah you you just immediately don't
do it yeah whereas to positively do
something will always in that sense
involve time because it might take a
little while before you're going to see
the results and so that's not time is D
anymore then yeah yeah exactly yeah even
if it's as quick as just thinking a sort
of FL it's already even if it's like a
s that quick of time is still and also
like you never you never start from that
like you would have started from a point
of view where it took time and you would
have taken it on faith that somebody
else told you you will end up there
which means you didn't use this advice
you just found one guy who was telling
you something and you followed that but
you never actually understood presently
what is that non- greed and how can I
abandon it you just somebody else told
you like do this and you will end up
with the opposite yeah that is why there
you know there's this whole idea of
applying an antidote like oh I feel ill
will I should practice m as an antidote
to the ill will but that's a that's
that's a misunderstanding like sometimes
it seems to me that's also sort of an
import from a more let's say scientific
or biological way of thinking like when
the when the body is heal yeah you might
find herbs and medications something
external to this body that you apply in
order to heal so on the material Level
there is something to say for this whole
logic of applying antidotes you can you
apply the antidote but you cannot take
that and then apply to the level of the
mind because that's a confusion yeah no
but even on the level of the body you
apply this medicine but did you
understand what the source of the the
problem was in the first place or did
the pain just go away yeah yeah so so
that's the thing like people can succeed
in developing love or whatever but if
you ask them what was that ill will that
you abandoned in the first place was it
just unpleasant feelings that came up by
themselves and if you look closely most
of the time that's the implication ill
will was just the fact that I didn't
feel the way I feel
now whereas that's if you that's not
what a will is no a will is not
unpleasant feeling a will is a choice
that you make on top of unpleasant
feeling and if you don't understand that
well again the only way you'll be able
to make progress is is through some
external information mhm yeah and you
and you will never be able to resolve
doubt as long as it stays on that
external level yeah yeah yeah because
you're okay do I have enough love
uhhuh yeah in that sense like it's never
enough because it's like I can cultivate
this kind of sort active external love
but that's actually wed in craving
because I'm chasing something yeah so
that when I come back I stop oh craving
is there again so I need to build up and
more and then more and then more it's
building up the discrepancy it's like
yeah it's it's
um you're you're you're trying to F fill
something up and at the same time
through that reaction you're emptying it
from like another side that you don't
notice yeah plus you need to then keep
maintaining that as well yeah right so
so that that cannot be let's say full
ease or as a as a goal because if it's
about cultivating positively these
states yeah if you stop doing that if
you feel that you're l 10 diminishes so
that you need to keep that you keep
maintaining it then you will be then you
will remain the dependent on those
activities and so that's not going to
result in Freedom because in order to
keep doing that again many other things
need to be in place that are beyond your
control so but the undoing once it's
undone it's finished basically yeah and
and positively nothing needs to happen
because nothing un wholesome can come
about anymore because you uprooted the
UN wholesome yeah for